hello everyone this is Frank de Freitas
and we have a very special guest in the
studio with us today Michelle Roy how
are you Michelle I'm good Frank how
about you I want to thank you for coming
out on such a cold day 25 degree below
zero wind chill I know not good not good
you don't live far from me I could have
done this with you on the phone so I
appreciate you uh coming in because I
like to do these live in the studio and
very rarely do I ever have a chance
because there's so many people in
holography which are scattered not only
across the country but around the globe
but it's just impossible to have people
come into the studio but it's nice to
have you here it's good to be here and
before we get started I would just like
to uh tell the listeners a little bit
about my Impressions with Michelle Roy
and why I'm so excited about the show
this week I got involved with the
freelance group for career and Workforce
Innovation and probably about a year and
a half to two years ago through my
involvement with Lehigh University and a
startup Science Museum called the
discovery of Science and Technology Bill
freed who is the president and CEO of
the freelance group was also at the
Discovery Center working on Workforce
Development and I was there setting up
their laser and holography programs
laser light shows and I would do
demonstrations for the public where they
would come in see the laser light show
but because it was an educational
institution we would or I would go over
all the different things that lasers
were capable of and what Holograms were
but I would also always tie in how
lasers are used in industry and science
technology art
Etc and Etc and Bill and I began to
speak and I learned that basically what
he does and Michelle you'll be able to
clarify this or you know take it a step
further is the bottom line for the freed
Lance group is the fact that the end
result is to be able to have people go
into the workforce and be matched
closely with their interests and what it
is that they need to do and Michelle you
can tell us a little bit more about that
but Michelle is also involved with the
freelance group and now what we're doing
is beginning to put programs together
for lasers and holography where I go out
and do my normal presentation of what
lasers are about and what Holograms are
but the freelance group and specifically
Michelle Willie who's going to be
working with me is going to give people
information and guide them along the
path of moving into the field of
photonics so this is a very good thing
and Michelle is a very special person
since I've had a chance to meet her and
I'm very happy that she's on the show
and I am extremely happy that they're
going to be involved with lasers and
velocity due to the fact that number one
she's a very very intelligent person but
combine that with the fact that she's
also sharp which if any of you get
emails from Dr cell and so or Dr
so-and-so and you read those emails and
you think how does this person even get
rest in the morning and go out you know
to perform anything
Michelle on the other hand had combines
that intelligence with the ability to
get dressed
and also the the level of
professionalism that she has and she's
also very highly polished with her uh
presentation skills so this is very good
for the field of holography and I'm very
honored to not only just have her in the
studio to be able to bring this program
to you but also the fact that she's
going to be working to get people
involved out there in the industry with
lasers and photonics and two of those
things that are happening quickly and a
Monday night January 24th at 7 30 at
Georgian Court College in Lakewood New
Jersey we're going to be doing a
presentation for the public on lasers
and holography in the Arts and Science
Center and also another one on May 6 at
the Smithsonian Institute in Washington
DC at the hershon Museum we will be
doing a very similar thing throughout
the day and Bill freed will also be down
there where you can meet Bill free as
well and I'm sure we'll have Bill free
on the show at some point he's down in
Florida right now while we freeze our
butts on in Allentown so Bill if you're
listening to this uh we're not happy
we're not happy yeah so Michelle why
don't we start off uh why don't you tell
us a little bit about yourself and also
a little bit about freelance okay well
as you mentioned at the beginning I work
with freelance and our work is in the
field of career development we do that
in a variety of ways working with
organizations and agencies to help them
provide better career development
services to people I guess probably I
should start by sort of defining you
know the whole idea of career
development yeah which is most people
don't even think about right if you're
going to go out and buy a stereo you
have all these books and magazines that
you're looking at to find out what the
frequency response is how many watchable
speakers handle blah blah but when you
go out for a job you have nothing right
yeah I think about when I first got a
job my first job out of college was as
an admissions counselor at a junior
college which I just into that I I had
no plans for what I was going to do I
hadn't thought about you know what are
my interests or abilities or where do I
want to go actually I think I just
didn't want to leave school so that was
a way to you know get paid for staying
in school and so I just sort of fell
into that job and I think a lot of
people do that so the idea of career
development really is that you've
thought about what your interests and
abilities are the things that you're
good at done some research on careers
that are out there and so forth and I'll
get more into that in a little detail
later on I think but just
here that you think about your career is
something that you
that your time an effort and Research
into then the same amount of time and
effort of research as you would put into
researching a stereo system or at least
or maybe even more but a lot of people
don't know how to do that they're not
they don't understand what resources are
out there they don't do a lot of
planning around their careers they don't
even think of themselves as having
careers they think of it as just you
know a job that's just how I pay the
bills so the the the freelance group is
really interested in helping people get
into careers where there's a definite
career path you've thought about what
you want to do and how you want to do
that to make you happier because really
the the bottom line is if we're not
happy with the work that we do then we
tend to not do a very good job with it
and we tend to not maybe be able to
progress the ways that we would like to
because we're just not into it so the
freelance group that's basically what we
do is work with you know individuals and
agencies and so forth to educate them
about the career development process and
you know how to effectively look for
careers my background actually I
mentioned my first job was in higher
education so I I'm familiar with the
higher education Arena and what kinds of
college majors are out there and that
kind of thing I then went from that into
Human Resources where the human
resources manager for a couple of
companies in the Lehigh Valley so I know
the kinds of things that employers are
looking for and how that whole how to
recruit you know when I get a resume and
you know what kinds of things do we look
at what do we look for in interviews and
so forth and then I actually worked for
a local organization a non-profit that
was involved in career development and
providing career development services to
clients to customers and so I you know
got a hold of that piece of the picture
so really my background has been in a
lot of different areas and now I have
the opportunity to really piece those
different areas together to help people
in you know identifying careers and and
moving forward in their careers so what
is a job exactly I know that I I imagine
through the U.S Department of Labor they
have different codes and everything
whether you happen to be a person that
washes dishes or you're someone who's a
microbiologist there's a category and a
code for that specific job and I don't
know if I've only had just the correct
thing for that right well onet is a way
of looking at jobs previously they've
had what they called the ooh the
Occupational Outlook Handbook and that
was primarily based on well they have
different categories of jobs you know
science and technology for example would
be a category and then there would be
specific jobs within that category and
the ooh that Occupational Outlook
Handbook was an annual publication that
the Department of Labor put out that has
descriptions of various jobs
excuse me it wasn't based on skills what
we're finding now and you bring up the
concept of onet onet is a new way of
looking at jobs that the Department of
Labor has come up with that's based on
skills and what people know how to do as
opposed to a specific job description
because I think what we're finding more
and more is that we're not going into
specific jobs necessarily we're using
constellations of skills in different
ways yes you there are specific names
for jobs and specific occupations
obviously but the most effective way for
people to be able to look for work or to
think about what careers to prepare for
is thinking about it in terms of what
their skills and interests are and so
the onet way of looking at work is
designed to help job Seekers or students
or whoever think of that to us in terms
of this would be a good job for me
because of my interests and abilities
this would be a good job for me because
of my work values for example which I
can get in get into that in a little bit
more detail later on so you know that's
basically it's it's sort of a paradigm
shift you know a different way of
looking at it do you know if holography
is listed with any of these things as an
actual job because there are
professional holographers obviously it
is a an industry that is growing there
are companies that are providing
Professional Services and creating
three-dimensional laser Holograms but I
think through some of the experiences
that I've had looking I have never seen
holography ever mentioned as a job right
not to my knowledge is there any you
know I have never seen I agree with you
I you know I've done a lot of research
too and you know in the Occupational
Outlook Handbook we never had
holographer I know that in the onet
database there's no such thing as
holographer part of the problem with
that or part of the reason for that I
guess I should say is that government
moves very slowly and let us not forget
that the Department of Labor who
publishes books like you know or uh has
owned and an Occupational Outlook
Handbook they are not necessarily as on
top of emerging careers which holography
is definitely anything in lasers and
photonics that's what we would call an
emerging career they're not as good
about getting that information so you
can have tons of stuff on you know how
to be a secretary you know clerical work
but they're not as good at coming up
with emerging careers as an example I
have not seen anything on webmaster
anything in web design now that's been
around for a number of years as well I
mean relatively speaking it's been
around for several years and there's
there really is nothing about that in
there I think they have some difficulty
getting their hands around those
sometimes
now the people who are out there right
now the Holo talk listeners that are
listening to this program I guess since
the government does this we'll do this
for this show we're going to break them
down into categories and I would say
that the majority of people would fall
into probably three categories we would
have the students who log on at a very
heavy rate right now because science
fair time is coming up and a lot of
schools pass out assignments to you know
and look into lasers and demography so
there's a lot of listeners that are
students there are a lot of teachers
which follow what's happening with the
field basically science teachers but
you'll find some art teachers in there
as well and then there are the
holographers themselves which is
category three which we could break down
into subcategories of professional
holographers who get their income you
know from doing holography and your
amateur and hobbyist holographer who has
probably been doing holography for years
but does it as a sideline you know to
their normal job that they go to each
day why don't we start off by you know
examining those categories of listeners
and then talk about how they would fit
into moving on if they were interested
in doing so ever to having career in
lasers and holography so why don't we
start with the students okay
in understanding Career Development
Frank there are stages that people go
through in their careers and so for
example when we're talking about
students and I I know that you have
listeners who are you know probably
maybe a few in elementary school but you
know middle school high school college
and so forth there are different stages
of looking at careers because of their
ages I mean obviously a sixth grader is
not going to be looking for a job next
year so they have different issues
compared to a college senior who
obviously will be looking for a job at
some point so so there's that whole
there are different stages that we're
looking at it uh following through you
know starting with younger listeners and
moving on all the way up the the first
stage of looking at careers is what they
call the career exploration stage and
that's where you're just really starting
to be aware of what jobs are out there
you're starting to be more aware of
yourself what are the things that I'm
interested in doing where do I show
Talent what kinds of abilities do I have
and so forth you're just kind of feeling
your way around seeing what's available
thinking about how do you fit in with
different things now the interesting
thing I think for students and and
thinking about middle school as an
example lots of people think well Middle
School's way too early to be thinking
about careers you know I mean they're
they're kids you know but that's way too
early it's not though because people
make decisions starting in middle school
about the courses that they're going to
take in high school that then might
prepare them for college courses
they don't take you know certain math or
science courses starting in middle
school they're not going to be able to
take the courses they need to take in
high school that you know then they
would need to take in college so now is
a good time to be thinking you know in
middle school is a good time to start
thinking about that stuff just so you're
sure that you have the foundations
educationally for what you may want to
do in the future so at the middle school
level we're really talking about
exploration starting to really feel um
feel out what kinds of jobs are out
there Beyond you know I know my dad does
this or my mom does that
and thinking about you know the
possibility that they want to go on for
higher education and being prepared you
know by taking the appropriate courses
school starts to be a little more
targeted obviously because students are
starting to make some decisions about do
I want to go to college do I want to get
a job right out of school I will say
this everything that I've seen about
two things one everything that I've seen
about wanting to be successful or be
able to make a lot of money as an
example which is what a lot of people
want to do and be able to find jobs you
need some level of higher education for
most jobs I've seen stats that say 80
percent of jobs are going to require
some type of post-secondary that that's
After High School kind of training or
education that doesn't necessarily mean
a four-year degree or a master's or a
PhD it could be you know a one-year
certificate or a two-year degree
technical training exactly but you need
something Beyond high school at this
stage of the game so that again they're
they're starting to be aware of you know
okay well I I want to meet I'm going to
go to college or I want to major in this
so you start to become more targeted
about the jobs that that you're
considering the interest areas that you
want to go into and exploring those
options and making plans you know for
for getting into those options once you
say someone goes to college then
obviously Career Development then
becomes a lot about taking the right
courses and finding a job and we have
you know I have some leads there are
some resources that people could access
in terms of jobs and lasers and
photonics but there that's when you're
starting to really get at specific
employers that you might want to work
for and that kind of thing then it turns
more into like job search now once
you're out there and that's what leads
us of course to the the holographers who
are have already graduated or you know
whatever who are out out there there's
that whole concept of moving along in
your career and so you need to be aware
of you know well here's where I am right
now in this job where do I want to be
what do I want to do what skills do I
need to to take me there what training
what experiences do I need and starting
to get into those make sure that you're
you know doing continuing education
you're reading a lot you know all of
those things to upgrade your skills so
you can move along on a career path some
people are happy you know I'll just stay
in this one job and I'm fine with that
but you know many people want to try
different things and it doesn't
necessarily mean climbing a ladder you
know where you're getting promotion it
could be trying out different you know
well I I have been in this kind of job
but now I'm going to make a lateral move
which is essentially the same level over
to something different that lets me try
out some different you know experiences
or learn some new skills or whatever
now when we get into the area of
teachers and Educators as as you're
aware the State of Florida just adopted
holography as part of the standards how
should teachers start to think should
they be thinking at all about that hate
not only am I teaching about lasers and
holography
kids could do this as a career as well
that's something teachers need to think
about at all a couple of things about
that one is I know that there are a lot
of states and and I don't know if
Florida is one of these or not who as
part of their state standards they have
what we call Workforce Readiness
standards which means that they are
supposed to be infusing Career
Development activities into the
curriculum exposing kids to Career
options helping them identify their
interests and abilities and so forth
for many state any state part of what
they have to do in order for a kid to be
able to graduate but the other part of
it is that part of the educational
process is preparing kids for success
when they leave high school and
obviously when we all leave school at
some point we have to get a job and so
helping kids understand early on and all
the way through the process how Career
Development Works how their interests
and abilities might fit in with various
jobs that are out there what their work
values are all of those things really
needs to be part of what teachers are
doing in the classroom they're
facilitating if you will the career
development of students so they need to
be exposing kids to different options
constantly because I my husband was a
teacher now he's a principal and he used
to laugh about you know kids would say
well why do I have to know this anyway
you know what what's important you know
what how is this relevant to me and I
think most of us ask that you know when
we're in an educational setting and one
of the ways to make class and things
relevant is by showing kids how this
ties into various career options and hey
you really like doing this guess what
you could do this for a living yeah I
should have said this at the beginning
there's an excellent book it's called do
what you love and the money will follow
it's to me the number one rule of career
development is for you to find out what
it is you love to do what do you have a
passion about what makes you you want to
get up and keep moving in the morning
what engages you and when you're doing
work that you really love then the money
will follow and I think you know that
too in your career Frank there's no
sense in people going out and doing jobs
that they hate it's just not it's not
productive in your life it's not
productive in any aspect people who hate
their jobs are really unhappy so
students need to be thinking about you
know what is it I really love to do how
can I get a job in that how can I turn
that into something I get paid for and
those are the people who are really
successful I mean Bill Gates who I know
is not necessarily a favorite of yours
but you know there's a guy who really
loves what he does and his passion led
him to great success that's obviously on
a larger more famous scale but frankly
um I love what I do and so I consider
myself successful you know I don't have
Bill Gates's money but I love what I do
and I I'm successful because I love what
I do so I think that that's really sort
of a moral responsibility almost that
teachers have an ethical responsibility
to help kids tap into what is it that
you love what is your passion let's look
at how we could turn this into something
really great for you when you leave
because that is what will guarantee your
success
all right that's my setbacks okay you
know very interesting stuff and what I
love about what I do is the fact that
when you call me in the middle of July I
have a nice holder on the raft that I
float on the pool that's right so if you
call me chances are I will pick that up
while I'm floating in the pool and talk
to you so that's something I love very
much about what I do yeah see I need to
get to the pool level I'm not there yet
now there's another sphere of people
involved with holography and as far as
people who are involved with photography
it's probably the largest sphere
and even more so than people who are
working professionally in the field are
the amateur and hobbyist holographers
who would just absolutely love to be
able to do this on a regular basis
if someone let's say John Doe or Jane
Doe out in the state of Minnesota has a
holography lab in their basement and
they feel like they've been working with
lasers and Holograms understands the
concepts very well and they decided that
they wanted to somehow move into working
with this thing professionally what
about them
a few things in regard to that obviously
and money taken back a step if I if I
could obviously someone who's in their
basement doing holography loving it has
already started to think about what
interests they have and what abilities
they have that can be related to a
career naturally the first step of
career development we call that and say
you know know yourself know who you are
so obviously that person has figured out
who they are and that this is something
that they really want to do
once you know that and and you've
narrowed it down to some occupational
areas which obviously that person would
have done then you need to do some
research and get some information one of
the things that I would and it depends
on how targeted the person wants to be
there are lots of jobs in you know using
lasers and photonics you can be in you
know a manufacturing or industrial
setting okay
um you could be an artist using
holography or you know using lasers you
could be involved in you could teach it
you know there are lots of different
ways you can use that Talent OR that
skill so one of the things the person
would need to do is be able is kind of
think about well what setting might I
want to work in how how would I want to
use this skill I know you know someone
who's probably moving more of an
artistic direction would be less
interested in going to work for some
manufacturer so that would be part of
that thought process what what setting
might I want to work in yeah then they
would need to do some research and there
are different way to research
occupations I have a lot of resources on
the web that people could go to to find
out about careers you can or in in
lasers and photonics one of the ways to
do that would be to look at actual job
openings and sort of get a sense for
what are what are the job descriptions
you know what kinds of things are people
doing in these jobs so that that could
help them Target you know what industry
or what area of
lasers they might want to go into
another one and frankly I think this is
probably the most valuable way to do it
is to talk to people in the field and
talk to people who are actually in those
jobs who actually do the thing that you
think you're interested in and find out
from them you know how how did you get
here what kind of you know job
experiences did you have prior to coming
into this position what Education and
Training did you have what advice do you
have for me you know I'm interested in
this career what do I need to have what
do I need to know in order to get into
this occupation what do I need to be
good at this occupation what do you
really do because another thing I'm
saying you know we'll do some research
on job descriptions as someone who has
worked at many organizations have job
descriptions and this whole list of
things that you do and then at the
bottom it'll say you know other duties
as assigned and you you think okay well
this is great this is what my job will
be and then you've got to work for them
and you find out your job is really all
other views that's a signed so you can
think this is you know what you're going
to be doing but until you actually talk
to someone in the field and really get a
sense of what reality is that's your
best way to do the research because then
you'll really know
um and I would talk to more than one
person because obviously you could talk
to someone who hates what they do and
they're going to give you a different
picture
um than someone who doesn't the great
thing about the internet of course is
that is another that's a way for you to
connect with people in various
occupations and so you might want to try
to you know hook up with people that way
and just that you know I'm just asking
you questions about your career and how
you got here most people are really kind
of excited to talk about themselves and
you know their work and the fact that
someone would be interested in them and
so you'll usually get some some good
information that way and then just sort
of General reading and research about
trends that are going on that might lead
to possible job opportunities I'm just
kind of thinking about well you know
where could I go colleges are another
source of information they're not that
many schools frankly that have you know
degrees or certificates in lasers it's
growing I mean I see that that it's
growing but there aren't a huge number
of schools that have those kinds of
programs
be another source of information and
also professional associations you know
there's like an association for optical
engineers and for photonics careers and
photonics things like that you know
contacting professional associations
frequently they will have information as
well and I imagine they're very eager to
share that information yeah I mean they
want to bring people into the that's
right part of their job is to get that
information out exactly sometimes if
it's not actually handed to you you do
have to take the first step that's right
and at least request the information
right I mean I think once you get the
information then sorry we should get the
information then you really have to go
back and say okay well how does this
match with what I want to do I've
mentioned a couple plans in our
discussion here the idea of work values
and that's something a lot of people do
not think about they think yeah I'm
interested in this yeah I would be good
at this but they don't think about how
it fits in with the rest of their lives
how when we talk about work values what
we're talking about is no matter what
job I have what's important to me what's
important to you Frank is that you can
float around in the pool answering the
phone right that is very important
that's right I know that's a work value
for you having that freedom and that
flexibility
so that's something to think about is
what are my work values could you know
what are the priorities for me in my
life if making a lot of money which is a
priority for a lot of people is a
primary work value then you probably
need to think twice about pursuing the
artistic aspect aspect of holography not
that you couldn't make money but I think
it would be a lot more difficult to be
really rich
just focusing strictly on that
um as opposed to you know being an
engineer or something so really thinking
about what are the things that are
important to me what are priorities for
me how does this work how does this job
fit in with the things that are really
important and that that is a key part of
the decision-making process because I
think a lot of people don't think about
that so I'm sorry I had interrupted you
no you interrupted and made some very
good points so I'm happy that you did
and I'm sure so are the listeners are
you still there yeah right
uh just TV let me know okay the last
group which is probably
I wouldn't say not as important because
well the reason I would say that is
because they already have jobs they're
professional holographers so they're
already out there they're getting a
check for doing holography each week now
all the Holograms that you see out there
someone has to produce them whether it's
in a retail store of holograms some
puppy or a security hologram on a
package or a hologram advertising in a
magazine those Holograms are being
produced by someone who's doing that
work who is a professional holographer
do we need to address them at all I mean
they're already there but is there
anything that you could say to them that
could yeah okay okay let me do that okay
um and this holds true for anyone who is
currently in a job or in a career I
don't care what field it's in
I think it's a good idea to periodically
reevaluate where you are in your life
and I'll tell you why a couple of couple
of years ago I was very unhappy in my
life in general so I sat down and uh
created for myself a mission statement
which you know some people are cringing
because that's just you know it's a
corporate but what I really wanted to do
was look at what are the things that are
important to me how do I want to use my
talents
what gives me fulfillment what gives me
satisfaction
so I wrote this mission statement and I
talked about you know what are the
things that I find really satisfying
about work
and then I looked at the work that I was
doing
and it didn't match
um and it hadn't occurred to me prior to
that that work was really what was
making me unhappy you know in my life I
just was going and yeah okay this is
fine if I hadn't done that reevaluation
I wouldn't have realized you know what
was going on so
not just because this is how I feel but
this is part of the whole career
development process I think
they do need to periodically reevaluate
where they are I chose to do that by
writing a mission statement and frankly
I would encourage people to do that
really think about what's important to
you and what talents you have and how
you want to use them but however you
choose to do that you need to look at
you know this is where I'm at where I am
where do I want to be if you're happy
where you are then you're okay until
your next reevaluation but if you're not
then you need to start thinking about
well where is it that I do want to go
because what happened with me is I did
that that mission statement and
reevaluated and then I thought about
okay well these are all these things
that I want to do what is work that I
could do that matches where I want to be
with my life
more research I looked at you know
talked to people got more ideas and
moved into a different career path if
you will choosing to go out and do my
work a little bit differently I had the
same skills that I was using actually
but I did it in a different way and so
that I think that what happens that you
do that reevaluation and then you say I
need to do research I need more
information to see how I could use my my
skills and talents differently or I need
more skills and talents because right
after what I ended up doing was leaving
my job and going out from to work for
myself
and I did a lot of
self-education during the first several
months doing a ton of reading talking to
people and so forth to build up my
skills in various areas and build up my
knowledge base so that it's that whole
concept of lifelong learning and
continuing to be current and build on
your skills and so forth so that you're
ready to go wherever wherever it is that
you want to go so I think that people at
my my long answer to the the question or
my short answer to the long answer is
that I think that people need to
reevaluate where they are if they're not
happy with where they are then they need
to do research and make some plans about
how they can get where they want to be
and that is how you get that career
satisfaction and how you can be
successful in a career is by doing that
constant career reevaluation there are
stats that I've seen that you know it
used to be that we would go in one job
and stay there for you know 40 years
um
but now there are statistics that
suggest that the average person is going
to change careers not jobs careers
five to six times in their lifetime well
and I'm living proof of that because I'm
what 36 years old and I'm already on
like my fourth or fifth career using the
same kinds of talents and abilities
building on those but using them
differently yes and that's really you
know how what what goes on as you think
about well how could I do something
differently but how do I have feel
growth to myself I know it's any sort of
fuzzy and you know love me kind of thing
but
it really you know to me it's really
important that and I think people lose
sight of this you really need to be
happy with what you're doing and so to
do that you need to think about what
makes you happy
let's put all this together now okay we
have our students we have our teachers
we have our amateur hobbyists and we
have our professionals that we've just
discussed now that we've covered that
let's move into the areas of how they
can do some of these things okay for
instance it doesn't matter if they're a
student now or if they're a teacher or
if they're amateur or professional how
would the listeners be able to get more
information on what training they would
need what education they would need in
order to pursue this field there are a
lot of resources on the internet
um related to that and frankly that
would be the most up-to-date place to go
as I said at the beginning I think that
a lot of government Publications and so
forth are just not really current the
internet is probably the most current
distribution method that we would have
there are a lot of websites that are out
there where you can get information on
you know what Education and Training you
need and so forth and I don't know do
you want me to give you the websites or
do you want to I mean I can give you the
URLs we could post a URLs on the whole
talk page and I would suggest that
people you know explore those some of
the websites where you can get more
information are as I mentioned earlier
in when I was talking about doing
research are colleges that have job
descriptions out there and so forth some
of them are websites for that are
specifically in the field of placement
where they're placing people in jobs and
lasers and photonics and so you can get
job descriptions and job information
from those and some of them are websites
for professional associations
that have online magazines and other
resources including job openings and so
forth that people could explore and get
more information from there so you know
those are some some prints if you will
you know in that you're reading them
online uh resources that you can use the
other thing as I mentioned earlier is
you know really talking to people in the
field and I was reading in New York
state they're having they have uh what I
think they call it the photonics
cluster that they've created up there
which is just a series of companies that
are all sort of gathered together that
have a lot of careers in lasers and
photonics that is potentially you know
calling the company up and saying you
know hey I just wanted to you know could
you put me in touch with someone to talk
to them about you know their career
um in this would that seem to say a
human resource like the human resources
manager yeah if in your reading I mean
like I mentioned some of these resources
that we have are professional
associations you can contact them many
times and say hey I just want to talk to
someone in the field and they can hook
you up
or like I said calling the company
asking the the HR manager you know could
I talk to someone yeah I mean that's
obviously can be difficult for people to
do you're kind of going out on the limb
to do it but it's really worth it if you
can talk to someone um it's much more
effective than than reading and if you
can actually try the job out even better
I missed that part um I mean the best
way to find out about a career is to
have an internship in it
um so I would love to try out being a
holographic
well and the work on that
so what you've brought with you today
besides the check for being on the show
you should be paying me this is good
information yes this is very good
information you brought with you a
number of resources that will cover the
following areas and let me see if I have
this straight here from the notes that
I've been jotting down while you've been
speaking
um you have resources on how listeners
would be able to find what educational
requirements and skills are needed to
work with lasers and orthography
howlisters will be able to find out what
training and education is available and
also about how listeners would be able
to find out what jobs are out there once
they have the training and the education
necessary to fill those jobs yeah and I
I also have some resources that on how
to identify your interests and abilities
oh okay so forth because you know some
people are pretty clear this is what I
want to do but others may want to play
around with things a little bit and so
there are some good online resources to
help you identify what you're interested
in abilities are and then how those
might fit into occupational area areas
and once again this is what freelance
does yep yeah this is what we do
although we don't do as much individual
client you know I I don't do career
counseling necessarily where I'm sitting
down you know one-on-one with someone um
I don't do much of that anymore only
only amateur
um that I'm counseling my friends and so
forth but uh yeah we work with agencies
and organizations to help them Implement
effective Career Development
um systems it's schools a prime example
of you know a crying need for career
development because it doesn't happen in
a context that makes sense to kids they
see Career Development as something that
you go to the guidance office for
um and actually at a lot of schools to
go to the guidance office to get your
schedule changed and that's about it
um so Career Development needs to be
something that happens in every
classroom so the kids really see okay
well what I'm doing is related to
something else you know I could do this
for a living kind of thing and there are
lots of easy ways to do that but yeah so
that's basically what we do okay well I
guess that about covers everything
unless you have anything else that you'd
like to add no I think we covered
everything in excruciating detail and if
you're a whole talk listener out there
and the I would say greater Metropolitan
New York area New Jersey area close to
Lakewood New Jersey I would like to
invite you to come out Monday night
January 24th at Georgian Court College
at Lakewood New Jersey where Michelle
and I will be will actually be there in
the daytime doing presentations as well
but the big ones for the public at night
at 7 30. come out and see what it is
that we're going to do with this we are
hoping that between the skills that I
have and the skills and talents that
Michelle and Bill free and others who
are involved with the freelance group
can combine and bring to the table that
we can have a positive impact on the
field of lasers and holography because I
know freelance is involved with things
in general they're not focused on laser
filmography but we don't have a special
effect in our hearts definitely there's
no pornography okay so I want to thank
you very much for coming over and I'd
like to take you out to lunch now that's
okay great see this is the advantage of
being able to come into the studio for
lunch after lunch
so thank you very much Michelle for
coming on the show and I hope the
listeners which I I don't hope I would
imagine that they enjoyed very much
listening to your presentation and the
valuable information that you were able
to come on and let the entire world know
about them and hopefully we can have
some impact on this field yeah that
would be great okay thank you for tuning
in and don't forget to tune in each and
every week when Hall talk brings news
and information and special guests like
Michelle this is Frank fragis see you
next week foreign